Guide to the Nora H. Faires Papers, 1854-2010 AIS.2011.06
ULS Archives & Special Collections
- The Splintered Cross, 1854-2010; V.
  - A Geneological and Biographical History of Allegheny County, 1889 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Atlantic Monthly "Pittsburg", 1868 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Baptist Conversions in Europe, c2007 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Bibliography, Undated (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Bodenftedt, "Die Rauchstadt Pittsburgh" (German), 1882 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Briefe Aus Amerika (German), c1930 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Catalog of Records Work, 2007 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - The Challange of a Heroic Past, c2006 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Chapter 1 "Foundation of Deutschtum" with Notes, Undated (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Chapter 2 Draft, 2010 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Chapter 3 "Crisis of Confessionalism, Undated (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Chapter Summaries, Undated (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Church Notes on Kin and Intermarriage, Undated (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Civil War in Allegheny County Notes and Data, c2007 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Collected Finding Aids, c2005 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Digital Document Printouts from Pitt Database, c2007 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - First Evangelical Lutheran, History 1837-1909, Chapter 1 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - First German Baptist Data, c2009 (Box 3, Folder 36-37)
  - First Methodist Notes, Undated (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - First Presbyterian Data and Notes, Undated (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - First Trinity Data, c2009 (Box 3, Folder 40-42)
  - First Trinity Lutheran 100th Anniversary History, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - First Trinity Marriages 1851-1882, Undated (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - German American Newspaper Clippings, 1974-1978 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Gerhard Oncken Data and Notes, Undated (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - German Baptists Data and Notes, Undated (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - German Methodist Data, Undated (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - German United Evangelical: A Short History, Undated (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Grace Reformed: Church Data, Undated (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Grace Reformed: Documents from the ASC (Some German), c2007 (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - Grace Reformed: Minutes of the Consistory, c1854 (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - Grace Reformed: Sunday School Record Book, C. 1954 (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - History of Alhegeny County: German Biographies, c2002 (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Henry Kurtz: Man of the Book, c1967 (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - Liturgical Churches, Undated (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - Miscellaneous Book Ideas and Notes, Undated (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - Occupational Patterns of Germans in Nineteenth Century Cities, Undated (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - Old Annotated Outline, Undated (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - Outline and Notes, Undated (Box 3, Folder 60)
  - Outline and Book Overview, c1989 (Box 3, Folder 61)
  - Pittsburgh Catholic Data, c2007 (Box 3, Folder 62)
  - Prospectus, Undated (Box 3, Folder 63)
  - Research Assistant Tasks, Undated (Box 3, Folder 64)
  - Research Initiation Proposal, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 65)
  - Research Proposal, c2005 (Box 3, Folder 66)
  - Rodef Shalom: Hebrew Primer (German), 1866 (Box 3, Folder 67)
  - Rodef Shalom: Data and Notes, c2009 (Box 3, Folder 68-69)
  - Schroeder: Corredpondence re: The Splinter Cross, 2010 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Schulte, "Memories", 1913 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Smithfield: Charter and Bylaws, 1942 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Smithfield: Pamphlets, Undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - St. John's Lutheran: Marriage Data 1849-1882, Undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - St. Mary's: Pamphlets, c1996 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Stuckenburg and Lutherans Notes, Undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Tree of Life: Data and Notes, Undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Zion Evangelical: Member List 1854, Undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Zion Evangelical: Data and Notes, Undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Audio/Visual Material, VI.
  - Audio Cassettes, 1993; 1.
    In December of 1993 Dr. Faires had an in-depth discussion with a male colleague (who is never identified) about her book The Splintered Cross. This nearly two hour conversation was recorded on an audio cassette and gives remarkable insight into the creation of the book. Not only does Dr. Faires lay out what she feels to be the theme of the book, but more importantly she goes over what she and the other speaker feel are the weaknesses. They also go over the historiography on the subject, and specifically what scholars/interpretations she intends to refute in her book. This discussion is very informative for those interested in the subject, and those with a weaker background in this area can gain an incredible amount of insight into it by listening. Both cassettes are copies of the same discussion, with the second being of noticeably better quality than the first.
    - Splintered Cross Discussion, 1993 (Box 4, Cassette 1)
    - Splintered Cross Discussion, 1993 (Box 4, Cassette 2)
  - Photographs, c1980; 2.
    In addition to the wide variety of research Dr. Faires did on churches within Pittsburgh, she also sought to document visual information as well. Located here are several color "snapshot" photographs and negatives of locations relavant to her work within Pittsburgh.
    - Eberhardt and Ober Brewery, c1980 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - St. Mary's Roman Catholic Church and Priory (Lochart & Pressley St.), c1980 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - St. Mathhew's Lutheran Church (North Ave), c1980 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Street Scene in East Allegheny (Northside), c1980 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Teutonia Mannerchor (North Side), c1980 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Voegtly German Evangelical Protestant Church (Northside), c1980 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Voegtly Church Cemetery (Troy Hill), c1980 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Negatives, c1980 (Box 4, Folder 18)